Yoonsu Kim

Ph.D. Student | HCI Researcher

✓ yoonsu16@kaist.ac.kr | kysoo816@gmail.com 🏠 https://yoonsu0816.github.io/

Research Interests

My research interests include around **Human-Computer Interaction**, **Human-Centered AI**, and **Human-AI** collaboration.

I am particularly interested in understanding the difficulties users face when interacting with AI systems, designing AI systems that enhance human capabilities from a Human-Centered perspective, and enabling people to effectively use and collaborate with AI to amplify their abilities.

Recently, I have been particularly interested in developing user-centered interactions that support **intent alignment in generative AI systems**, such as large language models (LLMs).

Through my work, I aim to contribute to helping people better utilize new technology.

Education

KAIST

Ph.D. in School of Computing

Advisor: Juho Kim

KAIST

M.S. in AI (Specialization: Human-AI Interaction)

Advisor: Juho Kim

POSTECH

B.S. in Computer Science and Engineering

Magna cum laude

Feb 2024 - Present

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Feb 2022 - Feb 2024

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Feb 2017 - Feb 2022

Pohang, Republic of Korea

Publications

Conferences and Journal Papers

[C1] Understanding Users' Dissatisfaction with ChatGPT Responses: Types, Resolving Tactics, and the Effect of Knowledge Level

Yoonsu Kim, Jueon Lee, Seoyoung Kim, Jaehyuk Park, Juho Kim *IUI 2024*

[C2] AI-to-Human Actuation: AI Proactively Induces Humans towards Favorable Sensing Conditions

Sungjae Cho, **Yoonsu Kim**, Jaewoong Jang, Inseok Hwang *IMWUT 2023*

Posters, Demos, and Workshop Papers

[D1] Applying the Gricean Maxims to a Human-LLM Interaction Cycle: Design Insights from a Participatory Approach

Yoonsu Kim, Brandon Chin, Kihoon Son, Seoyoung Kim, Juho Kim *CHI25 EA (Late Breaking Work)*.

[D2] LLM-as-a-tutor in EFL Writing Education: Focusing on Evaluation of Student-LLM Interaction

Jieun Han, Haneul Yoo, Junho Myung, Minsun Kim, Hyunseung Lim, **Yoonsu Kim**, Tak Yeon Lee, Hwajung Hong, Juho Kim, So-Yeon Ahn, Alice Oh *EMNLP 2024 Workshop on Customizable NLP (CustomNLP4U)*.

[D3] LLM-Driven Learning Analytics Dashboard for Teachers in EFL Writing Education

Minsun Kim, Junho Myung, Seon Gyeom Kim, Yoosang Yoon, Hyunseung Lim, **Yoonsu Kim**, Hwajung Hong, Alice Oh, Juho Kim, So-Yeon Ahn, and Tak Yeon Lee *EMNLP 2024 Workshop on Customizable NLP (CustomNLP4U)*.

[D4] Using Large Language Models to Diagnose Math Problem-Solving Skills at Scale

Hyoungwook Jin*, Yoonsu Kim*, Yeon Su Park, Bekzat Tilekbay, Jinho Son, Juho Kim (* Corresponding authors) L@S~2024~WIP

[D5] **Beyond Prompts: Learning from Human Communication for Enhanced AI Intent Alignment Yoonsu Kim**, Kihoon Son, Seoyoung Kim, Juho Kim

CHI 2024 Workshop on Getting Back Together: HCI and Human Factors Joining Forces to Meet the AI Interaction Challenge

[D6] RECIPE: How to Integrate ChatGPT into EFL Writing Education

Jieun Han, Haneul Yoo, **Yoonsu Kim**, Junho Myung, Minsun Kim, Hyunseung Lim, Juho Kim, Tak Yeon Lee, Hwajung Hong, So-Yeon Ahn, Alice Oh L@S~2023~WIP

[D7] **Towards Understanding the Challenges and Remedies in AI Application Development**Dae Hyun Kim*, **Yoonsu Kim***, Hyungyu Shin, Jinho Son, Juho Kim (* Corresponding authors)

KCC 2023

[D8] Demonstrating AHA: Boosting Unmodified AI's Robustness by Proactively Inducing Favorable Human Sensing Conditions

Sungjae Cho, Jaewoong Jang, **Yoonsu Kim**, Inseok Hwang *UbiComp/ISWC '23 Adjunct*

Experiences

HIS Lab (Human-Centered Intelligent System Lab in POSTECH)
Research Intern

Human-Computer Interaction, Human-AI Interaction, Embedded AI System

Jun 2021 - Feb 2022 Pohang, Republic of Korea

NAVER Connect Foundation

Manager of boostcamp Web & Mobile, AI Software Education **Feb 2020 - Feb 2021** Seoul, Republic of Korea

Neuromeka

Software Development Intern

Jun 2019 - Aug 2019Pohang, Republic of Korea

Android application development for robot manipulation and robot database management

Samsung Electronics Co.

Research Intern

Suwon, Republic of Korea

Department of Visual Display, AI • Big Data Lab

SK Telecom

Software Development Intern

Department of Service Platform

Jun 2018 - Aug 2018

Seoul, Republic of Korea

AI Technology Unit, Knowledge and Technology Cell

Scholarship

National Scholarship (Science and Engineering) 2017 - 2023

Global Leadership Program Mar 2018 - Feb 2020

Samsung Dream Class Scholarship Jan 2018 ~ Feb 2018

Leadership & Service

Leadership

HCI@KAIST Committee

Student Committee Mar 2024 - Present

KAIST-Google exploreCSR

Student Organizer Mar 2023 - Aug 2024

POSTECH Student Council

Director of Welfare Department Feb 2019 - Feb 2021

POSTECH Library Council

President, Vice President Mar 2017 - Aug 2019

POSTECH Reader's Club 6

(Awarded by Excellent Mentee) Feb 2019 - Dec 2018

POSTECH Reader's Club 5

Teaching

POSTECH Programming and Problem Solving (CSED101)

Teaching Mentor Feb 2021 - Dec 2021

Volunteering

KOICA WFK Korean Medicine Volunteer Group Overseas Medical

Volunteer Activities

Dec 2023 Krong Battambang, Cambodia

KOICA WFK Korean Medicine Volunteer Group Overseas Medical Volunteer Activities

Aug 2019 Toshken, Uzbekistan